また月が昇る
mata tsuki ga noboru
The moon is rising again,
また (mata) is an adverb, meaning "again" or "once more."
月 (tsuki) is a noun, meaning "moon."
が (ga) is a particle, used to mark the subject of a sentence.
昇る (noboru) is a verb, meaning "to rise," "to ascend," or "to come up."
This line likely refers to the natural cycle of the moon's phases, where the moon appears to rise in the sky at night and then set in the morning, only to rise again the following night. In the context of the song, this line may be used to symbolize the passing of time and the cyclical nature of life. The moon's rise may also be a metaphor for the narrator's emotions or inner struggles, which come and go like the phases of the moon.
今日が終わりだす
kyou ga owaridasu
and today is beginning to end
今日 (kyou) is a noun meaning "today."
が (ga) is a particle, used to mark the subject of a sentence.
終わり (owari) is a noun meaning "end," "finish," or "conclusion."
だす (dasu) is a verb meaning "to become," "to start to be," or "to begin to do."
Likely refers to the passage of time and the fact that each day comes to an end, eventually giving way to the next day. In the context of the song, this line may be used to emphasize the fleeting nature of the present moment and the sense of melancholy or sadness that the narrator is feeling as the day comes to an end.
願い奏でる | 言葉をのみこむ
negai kanaderu | kotoba o nomikomu
I’m gulping down the words of wishes I’ve made
The word "願い" (negai) refers to a wish or desire, and the verb "奏でる" (kanaderu) means to play or perform music. So, "願い奏でる" can be translated as "to perform wishes" or "to make wishes come true." The word "言葉" (kotoba) means words, and the verb "のみこむ" (nomikomu) means to swallow or gulp down. So, "言葉をのみこむ" can be translated as "to swallow words." In the context of the song, these lines may be describing the narrator's emotional state as they listen to someone or something (such as a song or a conversation) that evokes their wishes or desires. They may be feeling a sense of longing or yearning for something that they desire but do not yet have. The action of "gulping down" the words suggests a sense of urgency or desperation in the narrator's emotional state.
Friday Night 泣きだす
Friday Night nakidasu
Bursting into tears on a Friday night,
This line likely describes the narrator's emotional state on a Friday night, as they experience feelings of sadness and start crying. It's not clear from the lyrics what specifically is causing the narrator to feel this way, but it could be a variety of factors such as loneliness, heartbreak, or frustration with their circumstances.
The line "Friday Night" is likely a reference to the end of the week and the start of the weekend, which is often associated with relaxation and leisure. However, for the narrator of the song, Friday night seems to bring feelings of emotional distress.
君はまだ大丈夫
kimi wa mada daijoubu
but you’ll still be okay
The line "君はまだ大丈夫" (kimi wa mada daijoubu) can be translated as "but you'll still be okay." The word "君" (kimi) is a personal pronoun that means "you," and the phrase "まだ大丈夫" (mada daijoubu) means "still okay" or "still alright."
It's not clear from the lyrics who the narrator is addressing with this line, but it could be a friend or loved one who is also experiencing sadness or difficulty. The line seems to be meant as a message of encouragement and reassurance, reminding the person that they will eventually be okay despite their current struggles. It's possible that the narrator is trying to comfort themselves as well as the person they are addressing, using this line as a way to hold onto hope and optimism in the face of difficult emotions.
駆け出せ足音
kakedase ashioto
Run now, run
The verb "駆け出せ" (kakedase) means "to run out" or "to break out," and the noun "足音" (ashioto) means "footsteps."
In the context of the song, this line may be urging the narrator or someone else to take action and make a change in their life, rather than remaining stagnant or stuck in a difficult or unhappy situation. The line may be urging the person to escape from their current circumstances and pursue their dreams or goals, even if it means leaving behind their current situation or surroundings. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings of urgency or desire to make a change in their life, as they envision themselves breaking free and running towards their desired future.
明日を変えたい
ashita o kaetai
If you want to change tomorrow,
The word "明日" (ashita) means "tomorrow," and the verb "変えたい" (kaetai) means "to want to change."
In the context of the song, this line may be expressing the narrator's desire to make a positive change in their life or in their circumstances. The line may be a call to action or a statement of intention, indicating the narrator's determination to take control of their future and shape it in a way that they desire. The line may also reflect the narrator's feelings of hope and optimism, as they believe that they have the power to make a positive difference in their own life and the world around them.
なら  なら
nara, nara
in that case, in that case…
The word "なら" (nara) is a conjunction that means "if" or "in that case."
In the context of the song, these lines may be used to introduce a condition or premise for the actions or desires expressed in the previous lines. For example, if the narrator wants to change tomorrow, then "in that case" they may be suggesting that they are willing to take certain actions or make certain sacrifices in order to achieve that goal. The repetition of "なら" (nara) may be used to emphasize the importance or certainty of the condition being presented.
まだ  まだ  まだ
mada, mada, mada
Not yet, not yet, not yet
The word "まだ" (mada) means "not yet" or "still."
In the context of the song, these lines may be used to express the narrator's feeling that their goals or desires have not yet been achieved or realized. The repetition of "まだ" (mada) may be used to emphasize the narrator's sense of frustration or impatience, as they feel that they have more work to do or more time to wait before they can achieve their desired outcome. The lines may also reflect the narrator's determination to keep striving towards their goals, even if they have not yet reached them.
また夜空一周に
mata yozora isshuu ni
It’s making another round on the night sky
The word "また" (mata) means "again," and the phrase "夜空一周に" (yozora isshuu ni) means "around the night sky."
In the context of the song, it's not clear exactly what "it" refers to, but it could be the moon, which is mentioned earlier in the lyrics. If this is the case, then the line could be describing the natural cycle of the moon's phases, where the moon appears in the sky at night and then sets in the morning, only to rise again the following night. The line may be used to symbolize the passing of time and the cyclical nature of life. It's also possible that the line is a metaphor for the narrator's own emotions or struggles, which come and go like the phases of the moon.
満たして欠いて流れる
mitashite kaite nagareru
It waxes and wanes, and gets washed away
The verb "満たす" (mitasu) means "to fill up" or "to become full," and the verb "欠く" (kaku) means "to become empty" or "to lack." The verb "流れる" (nagareru) means "to flow" or "to be washed away."
In the context of the song, it's not clear exactly what "it" refers to, but it could be the moon, which is mentioned earlier in the lyrics. If this is the case, then the line could be describing the natural cycle of the moon's phases, where the moon appears in the sky at night and then sets in the morning, only to rise again the following night. The waxing and waning of the moon could symbolize the passing of time and the cyclical nature of life, and the action of "being washed away" could symbolize the fleeting nature of the present moment. It's also possible that the line is a metaphor for the narrator's own emotions or struggles, which come and go and are eventually replaced by new ones
時を眺める だけじゃ笑えない
toki o nagameru | dake ja waraenai
I can’t laugh if all I ever do is to watch the time
The word "時" (toki) means "time," and the verb "眺める" (nagameru) means "to look at" or "to gaze at." The phrase "だけじゃ" (dake ja) means "if all one does is" or "if that's all there is," and the verb "笑えない" (waraenai) means "to be unable to laugh."
In the context of the song, these lines may be expressing the narrator's feelings of boredom or frustration with their current situation. They may feel that they are just going through the motions of everyday life without any real purpose or enjoyment, and that they have nothing to laugh about or be happy about. The line may be a metaphor for the narrator's sense of stagnation or feeling of being stuck in a rut, and their desire to break free and find something to laugh about or something that brings them joy.
回る空うさぎ
mawaru sora usagi
The sky rabbit is spinning around
The verb "回る" (mawaru) means "to spin" or "to turn around," and "空うさぎ" (sora usagi) means "sky rabbit."
In the context of the song, it's not clear what the "sky rabbit" symbolizes or represents. It could be a metaphor for the narrator's own emotions or desires, which are constantly changing and moving. The action of "spinning around" could symbolize the narrator's feeling of being overwhelmed or uncertain about their future. Alternatively, the "sky rabbit" could be a purely fictional or mythical creature that is used to add a sense of whimsy or imagination to the lyrics.
君と明日はイコール
kimi to asu wa ikooru
You equal tomorrow
The word "君" (kimi) is a personal pronoun that means "you," and the word "明日" (asu) means "tomorrow." The symbol "イコール" (ikooru) means "equal."
In the context of the song, it's not clear exactly what is being equated with what in this line. It could be that the narrator is saying that they see their future as being closely tied to the person they are addressing (using "you" as a pronoun). Alternatively, the line could be expressing the narrator's belief that their own actions and choices have a direct impact on their future, and that they are responsible for shaping their own destiny. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's sense of hope or optimism about the future, as they see the person they are addressing as a source of strength or inspiration.
まけるな明日に
makeru na ashita ni
Don’t lose against tomorrow
The verb "まける" (makeru) means "to lose" or "to be defeated," and the word "明日" (ashita) means "tomorrow." The particle "な" (na) is used to make a request or give a command.
In the context of the song, this line may be urging the narrator or someone else to be determined and resilient in the face of challenges or obstacles that they may encounter in the future. The line may be a message of encouragement and motivation, encouraging the person to keep trying and not to give up, even when things get tough. The line may also reflect the narrator's own determination to overcome their own struggles and achieve their goals, despite any setbacks or challenges they may face.
背を向けたくない
se wo muketakunai
I don’t want to turn my back on it,
The noun "背" (se) means "back," and the verb "向ける" (mukeru) means "to turn" or "to face." The negative verb "たくない" (takunai) means "to not want to."
In the context of the song, it's not clear exactly what "it" refers to, but it could be the narrator's own feelings, goals, or circumstances. The line may be expressing the narrator's reluctance to give up or abandon their hopes or dreams, even when faced with challenges or setbacks. The line may also reflect the narrator's determination to keep moving forward and to stay positive and optimistic, even when things are difficult. Alternatively, the line could be a metaphor for the narrator's relationship with the person they are addressing, and their desire to remain connected and supportive of each other.
aa から  から
aa, kara kara
that’s why, that’s why
The word "から" (kara) is a conjunction that means "because" or "so."
In the context of the song, these lines may be used to explain or justify the actions or desires expressed in the previous lines. For example, the narrator may be saying "that's why I don't want to turn my back on it" in order to explain their determination to keep moving forward and to stay positive and optimistic. The repetition of "から" (kara) may be used to emphasize the importance or certainty of the reason being presented.
いま  から  から
ima, kara, kara
Right now, right now…
The word "いま" (ima) means "now" or "right now," and the word "から" (kara) is a conjunction that means "because" or "so."
In the context of the song, these lines may be used to emphasize the urgency or importance of the actions or desires expressed in the previous lines. The repetition of "いま" (ima) may be used to convey a sense of immediacy or to encourage the narrator or someone else to take action in the present moment. The line may be urging the narrator or someone else to seize the opportunity to make a change or to follow their dreams, rather than waiting or delaying. The line may also reflect the narrator's own feelings of determination or resolve, as they are ready to take action and make a positive impact in the world around them.
遥か  月を目指した
haruka tsuki o mezashita
I aimed for the distant moon
The adjective "遥か" (haruka) means "distant" or "far," and the noun "月" (tsuki) means "moon." The verb "目指す" (mezasu) means "to aim for" or "to strive for."
In the context of the song, the line may be a metaphor for the narrator's own goals or aspirations, which are distant and difficult to reach, but still worth striving for. The line may be expressing the narrator's determination to reach their goals, even if it requires a great deal of effort or sacrifice. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings of hope or optimism, as they believe that they can achieve great things and make a positive impact in the world, even if their goals are ambitious or seemingly out of reach.
今日の空は
kyou no sora wa
The sky today
The noun "今日" (kyou) means "today," and the noun "空" (sora) means "sky." The particle "は" (wa) is used to mark the topic of the sentence.
In the context of the song, this line may be describing the appearance or condition of the sky on the day that the song is set. The line may be used to convey a sense of the mood or atmosphere of the song, and to set the scene for the events that follow. It's also possible that the line is a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or emotional state, and that the "sky" represents the narrator's inner world or outlook on life.
彼方  西に流れた
kanata nishi ni nagareta
has been washed far away, to the west
The noun "彼方" (kanata) means "that way," "over there," or "far away," and the noun "西" (nishi) means "west." The verb "流れる" (nagareru) means "to flow" or "to be washed away."
In the context of the song, this line may be describing the movement or change of the sky from one place to another, using the direction "west" as a reference point. The line may be used to convey a sense of distance or separation, and to suggest that something has been lost or left behind. It's also possible that the line is a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or experiences, and that the "sky" represents the narrator's own inner world or outlook on life. The line may be expressing the narrator's sense of loss or longing, as they feel that something important has been left behind or has slipped away.
もう届かないや
mou todokanai ya
It’s beyond my reach
The adverb "もう" (mou) means "already" or "anymore," and the verb "届く" (todoku) means "to reach" or "to arrive." The negative verb "届かない" (todokanai) means "to not reach" or "to not arrive." The particle "や" (ya) is used to indicate a sense of resignation or acceptance.
In the context of the song, this line may be expressing the narrator's feelings of frustration or disappointment at being unable to achieve their goals or to make a positive impact. The line may suggest that the narrator has tried hard to reach their goals, but has been unable to do so, and is now resigned to the fact that they will not be able to achieve what they wanted. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings of isolation or separation from something important, and their inability to reconnect or regain what they have lost.
届かないや
todokanai ya
Beyond my reach…
The verb "届く" (todoku) means "to reach" or "to arrive," and the negative verb "届かない" (todokanai) means "to not reach" or "to not arrive." The particle "や" (ya) is used to indicate a sense of resignation or acceptance.
In the context of the song, this line may be expressing the narrator's feelings of frustration or disappointment at being unable to achieve their goals or to make a positive impact. The line may suggest that the narrator has tried hard to reach their goals, but has been unable to do so, and is now resigned to the fact that they will not be able to achieve what they wanted. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings of isolation or separation from something important, and their inability to reconnect or regain what they have lost. The repetition of the line may be used to emphasize the narrator's feelings of disappointment or resignation.
涙  星を濡らした
namida hoshi o nurashita
My tears have soaked the night
The noun "涙" (namida) means "tears," and the noun "星" (hoshi) means "star." The verb "濡らす" (nurasu) means "to soak" or "to wet."
In the context of the song, this line may be describing the narrator's emotional state, and their feelings of sadness or despair. The line may be expressing the narrator's sense of loss or disappointment, and their inability to find happiness or fulfillment. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings of loneliness or isolation, as they feel that their own emotions or struggles are too much to bear and are weighing them down. The "night" in the line may be a metaphor for the narrator's own inner world, or for the world around them, which seems dark and unforgiving.
In the context of the line "涙 星を濡らした" (namida hoshi o nurashita), the noun "星" (hoshi) means "star," but it may be used metaphorically to refer to the night.
The word "星" (hoshi) can refer to any celestial body that appears as a point of light in the sky, including stars, planets, and other celestial objects. However, the word can also be used more broadly to refer to anything that shines or glows in the darkness, such as a light bulb or a flashlight.
In the context of the line, the word "星" (hoshi) may be used metaphorically to represent the night sky, and the stars and other celestial objects that are visible at night. The line "涙 星を濡らした" (namida hoshi o nurashita) may be interpreted as meaning that the speaker's tears have soaked the night sky, which may be a metaphor for the speaker's feelings of sadness or despair, and for their sense of isolation or loneliness. The line may also be a metaphor for the speaker's own inner world, which feels dark and overwhelming due to their emotions.
今日の空は
kyou no sora wa
The sky today
The noun "今日" (kyou) means "today," and the noun "空" (sora) means "sky." The particle "は" (wa) is used to indicate the topic of the sentence.
In the context of the song, this line may be describing the state or appearance of the sky on a particular day. The line may be used to convey a sense of time or place, and to set the scene for the events that are described in the song. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or experiences, and the "sky" may represent the narrator's own inner world or outlook on life. The line may be used to convey a sense of hope or possibility, or to express the narrator's desire to break free from their current situation and to achieve something more.
彼方  夜に流れた
kanata yoru ni nagareta
has been washed far away, to the night
The noun "彼方" (kanata) means "far away," and the noun "夜" (yoru) means "night." The verb "流れる" (nagareru) means "to flow" or "to be carried away."
In the context of the song, this line may be describing the movement or direction of the sky, or the passage of time. The line may be suggesting that the sky has moved or changed in some way, and has been "washed away" or carried off to a distant place or time. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or experiences, and the "night" may represent the narrator's own inner world or outlook on life. The line may be used to convey a sense of loss or disappointment, or to express the narrator's desire to break free from their current situation and to achieve something more.
「もう泣くなよ」
「mou naku na yo」
“Don’t cry anymore”
The phrase "もう" (mou) means "already," "no longer," or "anymore," and the verb "泣く" (naku) means "to cry." The particle "な" (na) is used to make a suggestion or to give a command, and the phrase "よ" (yo) is used to give emphasis or to show strong feeling.
In the context of the song, this line may be used to give comfort or support to someone who is crying or feeling upset. The line may be expressing a sense of concern or compassion, and may be intended to encourage the listener to try to find hope or strength in difficult times. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or experiences, and may be used to express the narrator's desire to find a way to cope with their own struggles and to move forward. The line may be used to convey a sense of resilience or determination, and to encourage the listener to keep going and to keep trying, even in the face of hardship or disappointment.
遥か  月を目指した
haruka tsuki o mezashita
I aimed for the distant moon
The adjective "遥か" (haruka) means "distant" or "far away," and the noun "月" (tsuki) means "moon." The verb "目指す" (mezasu) means "to aim for" or "to strive for."
In the context of the song, this line may be describing the narrator's goals or aspirations, and their desire to achieve something that seems distant or out of reach. The "moon" in the line may be a metaphor for something that the narrator desires or values, and that they are working towards. The line may be expressing the narrator's determination or ambition, and their willingness to take on challenges and to overcome obstacles in order to achieve their goals. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or experiences, and may be used to convey a sense of hope or possibility, or to express the narrator's desire to break free from their current situation and to achieve something more.
今日の空は
kyou no sora wa
The sky today
The noun "今日" (kyou) means "today," and the noun "空" (sora) means "sky." The particle "は" (wa) is used to indicate the topic of the sentence.
In the context of the song, this line may be describing the state or appearance of the sky on a particular day. The line may be used to convey a sense of time or place, and to set the scene for the events that are described in the song. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or experiences, and the "sky" may represent the narrator's own inner world or outlook on life. The line may be used to convey a sense of hope or possibility, or to express the narrator's desire to break free from their current situation and to achieve something more.
数多  星を降らした
amata hoshi o furashita
brought forth a rain of many stars
The noun "数多" (amata) means "many," "numerous," or "countless," and the noun "星" (hoshi) means "star." The verb "降らす" (furasu) means "to bring forth," "to rain," or "to shower."
In the context of the song, this line may be describing the appearance of the sky, and the presence of many stars in the night sky. The line may be used to convey a sense of beauty or wonder, and to create a sense of awe or mystery. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or experiences, and the "stars" may represent the narrator's own hopes or dreams, or the things that they value or cherish. The line may be used to convey a sense of hope or possibility, or to express the narrator's desire to break free from their current situation and to achieve something more. The line may also be inviting the listener to consider the ways in which our own lives and experiences are shaped by the world around us, and the ways in which we can find meaning and purpose in life.
夢じゃないや！
yume ja nai ya!
This isn’t a dream!
The noun "夢" (yume) means "dream," and the particle "じゃ" (ja) is used to indicate negation or to show that something is not the case. The particle "ない" (nai) is used to show negation or to indicate that something is absent or non-existent. The particle "や" (ya) is used to give emphasis or to show strong feeling.
In the context of the song, this line may be used to express the narrator's sense of reality or to assert that something is true or real. The line may be used to convey a sense of conviction or belief, and may be intended to inspire the listener to believe in themselves and to pursue their own goals and dreams. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or experiences, and may be used to express the narrator's desire to break free from their current situation and to achieve something more. The line may be used to convey a sense of hope or possibility, or to encourage the listener to keep going and to keep trying, even in the face of hardship or disappointment.
夢じゃないや
yume ja nai ya
It’s not a dream…
The noun "夢" (yume) means "dream," and the particle "じゃ" (ja) is used to indicate negation or to show that something is not the case. The particle "ない" (nai) is used to show negation or to indicate that something is absent or non-existent. The particle "や" (ya) is used to give emphasis or to show strong feeling.
In the context of the song, this line may be used to express the narrator's sense of reality or to assert that something is true or real. The line may be used to convey a sense of conviction or belief, and may be intended to inspire the listener to believe in themselves and to pursue their own goals and dreams. The line may also be a metaphor for the narrator's own feelings or experiences, and may be used to express the narrator's desire to break free from their current situation and to achieve something more. The line may be used to convey a sense of hope or possibility, or to encourage the listener to keep going and to keep trying, even in the face of hardship or disappointment.